Um, hi. The moon is drifting away from
us. Where is it going? It's drifting
about 4 cm per year. That's about the
rate that your fingernails grow. And we
know that because astronauts left
mirrors on the moon. We shoot lasers at
them and time how long it takes for them
to come back. And it's getting longer.
So why is the moon leaving us? Blame the
tides. The moon's gravity pulls Earth's
oceans into a bulge. But the Earth spins
faster than the moon orbits. So the
bulge gets dragged ahead of the moon and
then in turn tugs the moon forward and
sort of flings it into a slightly wider
orbit. Billions of years ago the moon
was much closer and it would have looked
larger in our sky. But today the moon
and the sun look almost exactly the same
size in our sky, which is why we get
these perfect solar eclipses. But about
600 million years from now, Earth will
have its last total solar eclipse. But
will the moon ever fully leave us? No.
Because long before that, the sun will
swell into a red giant and swallow us
both. For optimistic science and tech
stories, subscribe.